-==www.RagBear.com==-
是, 首相  第2季第1集
本字幕仅供学习交流，严禁用于商业用途
-=破烂熊字幕组=-
翻译: vivitata
校对&时间轴: tpring
落水之人
艾伦 问题是这计划真的不错
Alan, it's really a very reasonable plan.
好 去跟国防部人事主管说啊
Tell that to the Chief of Defence Staff.
他怎么迟到了?不像部队作风
Why is he late? Not very soldierly.
就因为这计划 国防部乱成一团了
It's this plan. The Ministry's in turmoil.
艾伦 不过是军队调动而已 又不是俄国入侵
It's a relocation proposal, not a Russian invasion.
要是倒好了 我们有措施击退他们
Be all right if it was. We know what we could do to repel that.
真能击退吗?      不能
Could you repel it? No.
但不用真的费脑筋嘛
But we don't have to do any thinking about it.
我们站在首相立场上来看
Let's look at this from the PM's point of view.
我们有42万现役军人
We have 420,000 service personnel.
只有2万驻扎在北部
Only 20,000 are stationed in the north.
大家几乎都在南部
Almost everything's in the south.
海军在朴茨茅斯 空军在贝德福德
Navy at Portsmouth, Air Force in Bedford
陆军在阿尔德肖特
and the Army in Aldershot.
基本没人在沃什湾以北 高失业率地区
Almost nothing north of The Wash where the unemployment is.
很多军人来自北方      对 可他们在南方消费
Servicemen come from the north. But spend in the south.
没办法      怎么?
Inevitable.
他们人在那里嘛
That's where they are now.
况且 北方也没有可消费的 对吧?
Anyway, there's nothing to spend it on in the north, is there?
国防部人事主管来了      汉弗莱 这做不到...
Chief of Defence Staff. This cannot happen...
别跟我说 我支持你 可这计划太合理了
Don't attack me, I'm on your side, but it is a strong argument.
调20至30万军人去北方
Move 200,000 service personnel up north
能创造无数就业机会
and you create masses of civilian jobs.
勤杂人员 补给 建筑 车船修配
Clerks, suppliers, builders, vehicle maintenance.
3万份军饷花在商店里
300,000 extra pay packets spent in the shops.
几千人你不能说调就调啊
You can't move thousands of men like that.
军队不就这样吗      那还能调回来
I thought that's what you did with armies. You bring 'em back!
这一去就回不来了
This'd be permanent.
盖伊 有军人可以永久驻扎在北方吗?
Guy, can any servicemen be stationed permanently in the north?
低阶的大概可以 下级军官
I suppose other ranks, junior officers,
可你不能让高级军官
but you can't ask senior officers
一辈子住在北方
to live permanently in the north!
他们的夫人受不了
The wives wouldn't stand for it for one thing.
子女上学也是难题
Children's schools.
据我所知 北方也有学校吧
I understand there are schools in the north of England.
对 那哈罗德(伦敦豪华商场)呢? 温布尔登呢?
What about Harrods? What about Wimbledon?
赛马 赛艇 陆军海军俱乐部呢?
Ascot? Henley? The Army and Navy Club?
我指的是整个文明 北方都没有
I mean civilisation, generally! It's just not on!
盖伊 内阁今天下午就要讨论了
This is being discussed in Cabinet.
得拿出严肃理由
We need more serious arguments
光说军官夫人远离豪华商场可不行
than senior officers' wives being 300 miles from Harrods.
还不够严重? 你我都可能要调过去了
What's more serious?! Chaps like us might have to move up there!
就没有战略上的反对理由吗?
But are there any strategic arguments against the move?
战略能扯出任何理由
We can find those against anything.
经得起民间专家的论证吗?
But would they stand up to expert scrutiny?
不会让民间专家论证的
They won't get expert scrutiny.
我们会列为机密 国防部惯例
We'll make it top secret like we always do with defence.
只给首相过目
Prime Minister only.
那绝对没有专家论证了
Then they certainly won't get expert scrutiny.
可我在想
But I wonder whether we might not do
我们能不能踢人而不踢球
better to play the man instead of the ball.
哪个人?      就业部长
Which man? The Employment Secretary.
计划总归是他提的      没错
This was his suggestion. Ah, yes.
向首相暗示
Suggest to the PM
就业部长阴谋反对他
the Employment Secretary is plotting against him.
有吗?      没有 我没听说
Is he? Not as far as I know.
可问题在于
But the question is whether
能否让首相相信他有
the Prime Minister can be made to believe that he is.
有机会除掉他吗?
Any chance of getting rid of him?
首相? 他刚被驯化啊      不 就业大臣
The PM? He's only just house-trained. The Employment Secretary.
霍华德上将 你难道是说
Field Marshal, are you suggesting
卑微的公务员有权擅自撤换
humble civil servants should presume to remove
女皇政府的内阁大臣?
a member of HM Government from Cabinet?
对      不可能
Yes. Out of the question.
只有首相能撤换大臣
Only the Prime Minister can remove ministers,
可如果首相怀疑
but if the Prime Minister came to suspect
一个内阁成员的忠诚...
the loyalty of a member of his Cabinet
只有重度妄想狂
Only someone with paranoia
才会怀疑就业大臣搞阴谋
would suspect the Employment Secretary of a plot.
真的? 那我们有希望了
Really? Then we're in with a chance.
好 其它事宜 就业大臣
Other business. Employment Secretary,
你提请审阅你的报告
you wanted views on your paper.
对 首相 我的计划旨在降低东北部失业率
Yes, my plan to reduce unemployment in the northeast
通过将某些国防机构搬迁过去
by moving various defence establishments up there.
国防部长 你意下如何?
Defence Secretary, what's your view?
我知道 一眼望去
I know, on the face of it,
这一计划貌似减轻了
this plan looks as though it benefits
贫困地区就业压力
employment in depressed areas,
但据我理解 靠的是
but this is to be achieved, as I understand it,
重新部署大多数国防机构
by relocating most defence establishments.
与国防部的干系 和与就业部一样大
This affects the Defence Department as well as Employment.
我需要时间做可行性研究
I need time to do a feasibility study.
还有人有意见吗? 快提
Anybody else have an opinion? Quickly.
首相 我不太了解
I don't know much about it,
不过听起来像是剧变
but it does sound a serious upheaval.
耗资巨大      影响深远
Expensive.         A big move.
我支持这项提案
I'm in favour of the proposal.
我也是      绝对的
So am I. Absolutely!
看起来国防大臣要孤军奋战了
Looks as though the Defence Secretary is in a minority of one.
不过首相 我是国防负责人
I am the responsible minister.
这是领土防卫问题
The defence of the realm is in question.
很好 我们周五的会议上再深入讨论
We'll have a full discussion at our next meeting on Friday
然后提交内阁表决
and then put it to Cabinet for approval.
太好了 谢谢 首相
Thank you.
我能否要求会议纪要里记上
May I request that it be noted in the minutes
内阁委员会支持我的提案
that the Cabinet Committee was in favour of my plan
仅有一人反对?
save for one member?
是被重组部门的负责人 这问题可大了
The member whose department would be reorganised. It's a problem.
能否提请国防大臣注意
May I remind the Secretary of State for Defence
举凡问题 都伴随着机遇?
that every problem is also an opportunity?
好啊 好啊
Hear hear!
国防大臣担心
The Secretary fears that
这可能造成某些不期之遇
this may create some insoluble opportunities.
胡说 没那事
Nonsense.
首相      还在啊 汉弗莱?
Er, Prime Minister... Oh, still here, Humphrey?
对 不知能否跟您谈谈
Yes. I wonder if I could have a word about
就业大臣的提案
the Employment Secretary's plan.
行 提案不错吧?
Yes, terrific, isn't it?
国防部人事主管不大喜欢
The service chiefs aren't entirely happy.
好呀
Good.
首相 您在认真听我说吗?      当然
Do I have your full attention? Of course you do.
我顺便看看会议纪要
I'm just reading these notes.
首相 黑斯米尔发生大地震了
Prime Minister, there's been an earthquake in Haslemere.
好呀
Good.
什么?      人事主管不喜欢这个计划
What? The service chiefs don't like this plan.
当然 夫人们去不成网球赛和商场了嘛
Taking their wives away from Wimbledon and Harrods!
首相 您怎能这么说
Prime Minister, that is unworthy.
这和他们的私心毫无关系
Their personal feelings don't come into it.
反对纯粹出于战略考虑
Their objections are entirely strategic.
战略 可不是嘛
Oh, strategic, of course.
海军部需要深海港
Admiralty needs a deep-water port
所以要设在巴思 离海30里
so that has to be at Bath 30 miles inland.
水兵是保卫挪威(英国以北)的
The job of the Marines is to defend Norway,
所以驻扎在普利茅斯(英国西南)
so we station them at Plymouth.
陆军车辆在苏格兰检测
Army vehicle trials take place in Scotland,
所以军工部当然得在萨里(英国东南)
so the engineering establishment has to be in Surrey.
这些都是特例
Well, these are just isolated examples.
我还有700个"特例"呢
I've got another 700 isolated examples.
你为什么反对它 汉弗莱?      我 首相?
Why are you against it, Humphrey?
我保证我绝无反对
I assure you I'm not against it.
我只是为您提出合理的问题
I'm simply furnishing you with the appropriate questions
比如成本
like that of cost.
这就是妙处 它能挣钱
That's the beauty of it it makes money.
把南方那些贵重机构卖了
We sell all these expensive properties in the south
一路北上
and move "up north"!
您觉得就业部长干得好吗?
You think the Employment Secretary has done well?
是啊 他这人不错      我完全同意 首相
Indeed I do. He's a good chap. Oh, I quite agree.
简直才华横溢
Absolutely brilliant.
智慧超群
Superb intellect.
步伐稳健 手腕出众 形象高大
Strong footwork, excellent elbows. A major figure,
毫无疑问
without a doubt.
也没那么好吧      但他这人不错 您说是吧?
He's not that good. But he is a good chap, wouldn't you say?
是啊 我刚说过      对 当然 很得人心
I've just said so. Oh, yes, indeed. Very popular.
是吗?      可不是嘛
Is he? Oh, yes!
也没那么得人心吧?      当然了
Not as popular as that, surely? Oh, yes.
在白厅和议会各党 左右逢源      恐怕是的
In Whitehall and with the parliamentary party. I suppose, yes.
据说和草根阶级也是      有吗?
And with the grass roots, I'm told. Are you?
在内阁也一呼百应 对吧      是吗?
And he has quite a following in Cabinet, too. Does he?
实际上 已经有人在说
People are beginning to talk about him
让他接任首相了
as the next Prime Minister.
什么...你什么意思?      当然是您决定退休之后
What... What do you mean? Oh, I mean when you decide to retire.
我没要退休啊 我才刚上任
I'm not going to retire! I've only just got here!
他们怎么就谈起下一任首相了?
Why are people talking about the next PM?
我坚信这不过是宏观预测 首相
I'm sure it's just general speculation.
他本人有意当首相吗?      就算他有...
Does he want to be Prime Minister? Well, even if he does...
您当然也不至于怀疑他的忠诚吧
...surely you've got no reason to suspect his loyalty?
他总没有在拉帮结派吧 有吗?
He isn't planning to build up a personal following, is he?
没有吗?
Isn't he?
有吗?      他成天都在做演说
Is he? Spends a hell of a lot of time making speeches.
对 但这只是履行大臣职责 我相信他
Only as a loyal minister. I'm sure
一定会在演讲中替您美言吧?
he pays tributes to you in them, doesn't he?
有吗? 伯纳 把他最近6次讲话拿来
Does he? Bernard, get me his last six speeches.
好 我正要去 首相
Er, yes, I'm just getting them, Prime Minister.
他老在茶室里跟后座议员聊天
He chats up back benchers in the tea room.
您吩咐大臣们多与党派和下院交流的
You told ministers to take more trouble to communicate.
还请他们参加晚宴      他有吗?
And he has them round to dinner parties. Oh, does he?
让人担心啊      就业大臣的讲话 首相
Worrying. The Employment Secretary's speeches.
肯定在讲新任首相乃国家之契机
I'm sure he talked about the new PM bringing new hope to Britain,
带来新时代的黎明
the dawn of a new age.
就那本小册子
You know, that leaflet
您让政党总部下发各大臣和选区的
you told Party HQ to issue to all MPs and constituencies.
没有 一句都没有      这可奇怪了
No, not a word. Oh, now that IS odd.
何止奇怪 简直可疑 相当可疑
It's more than odd, it's suspicious. Bloody suspicious!
就算是 他总不会阴谋反对您吧
Even so, he surely isn't actively plotting against you.
他不会吗?      他会吗?
Isn't he? Is he?
我怎么知道他不会?      我相信您自有办法明察
How do I know he's not? I'm sure you can always find out.
给我接组织秘书 伯纳
Get me the Chief Whip.
是 首相 接组织秘书
Yes, Prime Minister. Get me the Chief Whip.
马上      马上 您好 组织秘书
Now! Now! Oh, hello, Chief Whip.
您在12号吗? 首相有急事要见您
Are you at No.12? The PM wants to see you urgently.
马上      马上 谢谢
Now! Now! Thank you.
汉弗莱爵士      什么 伯纳?
Sir Humphrey. Yes?
我刚听到的事太可怕了      什么事?
I'm troubled by what I've learned. What?
我觉得像个睁眼瞎
I feel I've had my eyes shut.
我从没察觉内阁有阴谋反对首相
I never realised there was a plot against the Prime Minister.
有吗? 真有意思
Is there? How interesting.
可您说有的      没有 伯纳 我什么也没说
But you said there was. I said nothing, nothing at all.
您是说...哦
You mean... Oh.
您知道有没有阴谋吗?      不
Do you know if there is a plot? No.
不知道还是不存在?      对
No, there isn't? Or, no, you don't know? Yes.
汉弗莱爵士 就业大臣到底干了什么?
What exactly has the Employment Secretary done?
眼下还没有 伯纳 我们得保持这个状态
Nothing yet, and we must keep it that way.
可他的计划不好吗?
But isn't his plan a good one?
对谁?      对国家
For whom? The country.
这不是重点      为什么?
That is hardly the point. Why not?
伯纳 你离职之后 打算去哪里?
Bernard, when you move on from here, where do you plan to go?
我...我不知道
Well, I... er... I... I don't know.
做副秘书长 主管国防采购如何?      天啊...
Like to be in charge of defence procurement? Oh, gosh...
在散德兰 或者贝里克
In Sunderland or Berwick
或者萝西毛?      这是地名吗?
or Lossiemouth? Is that a place?
萝西毛? 你以为是什么?      狗粮牌子
Lossiemouth? What'd you think it was? A dog food.
如果就业大臣得逞
If the Employment Secretary has his way,
你就要吃三年萝西毛了
you may get a diet of Lossiemouth.
明白?      明白
See? Yes.
这怎么可能对国家有益?      绝对没有
How can it be good for the country? It can't.
可您为什么建议找组织秘书
Why will the Chief Whip
证实不存在的阴谋?
confirm a plot that doesn't exist?
因为他只能绕弯子 组织秘书不能说没有阴谋
He's bound to hedge. The Chief Whip cannot state that
以防真的有
there's no plot just in case there is.
他得给自己留后路 早安 组织秘书
He has to cover himself. Good morning.
您能去私人办公室等吗?      好
Could you wait in the private office?
伯纳 你进去 回头向我通报谈话内容
Bernard... now go in there and inform me of their conversation.
我不一定能说 也许是机密
I'm not sure I can. It might be confidential.
伯纳 这关系到国土安全 还有政府稳定
Bernard, the matter at issue is the stability of the government.
可您只需知道您需要知道的事
You only need to know things on a need-to-know basis.
我需要知道一切
I need to know everything!
不然我怎能判断我需不需要知道?
How else can I judge whether or not I need to know it?
所以您不需要知道的事
So you need to know things even
您也需要知道?
when you don't need to know them?
您需要知道 不是因为您需要知道
You need to know them because you need to
而是为了知道您是否需要知道
know whether or not you need to know.
就算您不需要知道 您也需要知道
If you don't need to know, you need to know so
才能知道您不需要知道
you know there was no need to know.
对      好 这就很清楚了
Yes! Good. That's very clear.
组织秘书来了 首相
Chief Whip, Prime Minister.
早安 首相
Morning, Prime Minister.
最近情况怎样 组织秘书?      挺好的 怎么了?
How are things going, Chief Whip? Oh, quite well, really. Why?
你没注意到什么?      眼下是比较艰难
You've noticed nothing? Well, it's a difficult time.
后座议员骚动不安...
Bit of unrest on the back benches...
您...到底想说什么?
What... did you have in mind precisely?
阴谋 对领导权的挑战
A plot. A leadership challenge?
啊 对...
Ah. Yes...
说实话 我还没有确凿证据
Well, actually, I have no real evidence of anything.
可你起了疑心?      我常年都起疑心的
But you have suspicions? Oh, I always have suspicions.
到什么地步了?      只到很...很...
How far has it got? Oh, only a very... um... very... um...
初期?      初期 据我了解
Early stage? Early stage. As far as one can tell.
你不该找他谈谈吗 告诉他我察觉了?
Should you have a word with him?
我不想让内阁失去他
I don't want to lose him from the Cabinet.
我只想控制他
I... just want him under control.
也许您应该亲自找他谈谈
Perhaps you should have a word with him yourself.
不不 暂时不要 除了他还有谁?
No, no, no, no. No, not at this stage. Who else is involved?
除了...
Apart from...
除了达德利(就业大臣) 当然      达德利
Apart from Dudley, obviously. Dudley?
对 当然 除了达德利 除了达德利还有...
Yes, of course, apart from Dudley. Well, apart from Dudley...
现在说有点为时过早
Well, it's... um... It's a bit early to say.
也许没什么事
There may be nothing in it.
杰弗里 我可冒不起这个险      不 当然不行
I'm not taking any risks. No, absolutely not!
我再下去问问
I'll go and make a few more enquiries.
达德利?
Dudley?
对
Yes.
我猜首相支持提案
I presume the PM's in favour of the scheme
是因为它能降低失业率吧
because it'll reduce unemployment.
它会显得首相在降低失业率
It'll look as if he's reducing unemployment.
或者显得他在设法降低
Or look as if he's TRYING to reduce it.
尽管他只是设法显得
Whereas he's only trying to look as if
他在设法降低失业率
he's trying to reduce unemployment.
对 因为他担心显示不出他在
Because he's worried that it doesn't LOOK as if
设法显得设法降低失业率
he's trying to look as if he's trying to reduce it.
你打算怎么阻止?
So how are you going to stop it?
首相开始怀疑
The PM has come to suspect
这计划也许是就业大臣
the plan may be the start of a leadership bid
夺取领导权的第一步
by the Employment Secretary.
真荒唐 可职位越高
How ridiculous, but the higher the office,
妄想症也越重
the higher the level of paranoia.
幸好 是这样的 可妄想症需要动力
Fortunately, yes, but paranoia needs something to feed on.
没有比媒体泄密更好的动力了
Nothing like press leaks for paranoia fodder.
这个标题怎样
What if there should be a headline about
"惨遭首相封杀"?
being blocked by the Prime Minister?
有人失足落水了      幸运的话
Man overboard! With any luck.
可问题是 内阁秘书不能参与泄密
But the trouble is a Cabinet Secretary cannot be party to a leak.
不 当然不能      然而前任内阁秘书...
No, of course not. Whereas a FORMER Cabinet Secretary...
可想而知 作为信息自由运动主席
Presumably, as chairman of the Campaign for Freedom of Information
你有责任把某些事实公布出去吧
you have a... a duty to make certain facts available.
你是暗示我把机密信息透给媒体吗?
Are you suggesting I give confidential information to the press?
当然不是 阿诺德
Certainly not, Arnold.
这是机密假信息
This is confidential disinformation.
啊 那就不同了
Ah, that's different.
抱歉 这是给首相的晚报吗? 能看看吗? 多谢
Oh, excuse me. Is that the evening paper for the Prime Minister? May I?
很好 听着 我有急事找他谈
Ah, good. Look, I have to have an urgent word with him.
不知你能不能稍后送进去
I wonder if you'd be kind enough to bring that in in,
过3分钟吧 谢谢
say, three minutes. Thank you.
谢谢 伯纳      汉弗莱 我知道怎么回事了
Thank you, Bernard. Humphrey, I know what's been going on!
您知道了?      对 我知道了
You do? Yes!
有人背着我暗中勾结
A scheme has been hatched behind my back,
一场背信弃义的阴谋 我绝不会轻饶
a disloyal, treacherous plot, and I won't tolerate it.
我跟组织秘书谈过了      怎样?
I've spoken to the Chief Whip. And?
他说没证据 但他也怀疑 他要去查问
He says he has his suspicions. He's going to make enquiries.
等有了确凿证据再向我汇报 你看
He can't tell me more till he has something solid. You see?
什么?      就业大臣在搞阴谋
What? The Employment Secretary is plotting!
还不懂 汉弗莱?      我只能说 我太惊讶了
Come on, Humphrey! Well, I must say, I am surprised.
我总以为您的内阁大臣都很忠诚呢
I should've thought all your Cabinet were loyal.
忠诚 你知道内阁大臣的忠诚是什么
Loyal! You know what loyalty in a Cabinet minister means?
他对自己下台的恐惧
His fear of losing his own job is
稍稍压过想取代我的愿望
slightly greater than his hope of pinching mine.
对 但你们有集体负责制...
But with collective responsibility...
集体负责 就是政府一出成绩
If we do something popular,
他们都放风说是他们的主意
they leak that it was their idea.
要是失败了 就放风说他们本来就反对
If it's unpopular, they leak they were against it.
我们政府的原则是集体不负责制
We're governed on the principle of collective irresponsibility.
他们为什么想取代您?
Why do they want your job?
因为政府里就我一个人
Because I'm the only member of the government
不可能下周被踢到北爱尔兰去
who can't be sent to Northern Ireland next week.
我不能相信就业大臣真的在阴谋反对您
I can't believe that the Employment Secretary is plotting against you.
你还要什么证据?
What more proof do you want?
首相 把国防机构搬到北方的提案
This proposal to send defence establishments up north
肯定会泄漏给媒体吧?
is bound to be leaked to the press.
肯定会      如果媒体说是他的计划
Bound to be. If it were leaked as HIS plan,
您的怀疑就证实了 但我相信计划会被归给政府
it'd confirm your suspicions, but I'm sure it'll go out as a government plan.
你相信? 我可不信      啊 晚报来了
Are you? I'm not. Ah, the evening paper.
老天啊 看 流氓 你要的证据 汉弗莱
Good God! Look! Swine! There's your proof, Humphrey!
天哪 我太震惊了
Good heavens, I'm astonished.
"白厅知情人士透露 这份创意计划"
"Sources in Whitehall report that this imaginative plan,
"由就业大臣一手提出"
"an initiative by the Employment Secretary,
"却惨遭首相封杀"
"has been blocked by the Prime Minister"?!
他怎么敢这样
How dare he!
他怎么敢? 我...我...
How dare he! I'm... I'm...
无话可说?      无话可说
Speechless? Speechless!
我一路为他保驾
I've backed him all along!
我为他的破提案力排众议
I've fought for his sodding plan!
他第一个内阁职位就是我给的
I gave him his first Cabinet post,
我待他像亲生儿子
treated him like a son!
这就是我得到的报答
This is the thanks I get!
内阁同僚之负义 何猛于毒蛇之尖牙啊
How sharper than a serpent's tooth it is to have a thankless Cabinet colleague.
是嫉妒 达德利满心嫉妒
It's envy. Dudley is consumed with envy.
这是七宗达德利罪(死罪)之一
It's one of the seven Dudley sins.
谢谢 伯纳
Thank you Bernard
首相 要不要起草接受他辞呈的信?
Prime Minister, shall we start to draft your letter accepting his resignation?
没那么简单 他不会承认泄密
It's not that simple. He'll deny he leaked,
我以什么理由炒他?
so why am I sacking him?
再说 他变成后座议员更危险
He'll be more dangerous on the back benches.
炒了他 他都不用假装忠诚了
Sacked, he doesn't have to pretend to be loyal.
那您要顺着他的计划来?      不行 现在不行
So you mean you'll go ahead with his plan? I can't. Not now.
会显得像他击败了我 这个险不能冒
It'll look as though he's defeated me. I can't risk that.
计划确实不错
It's a good plan.
那么 也许...不不 我...
So... perha... Er... no, no, I...
首相 您不会不知如何是好了吧?
Prime Minister, you're not being indecisive, are you?
不 不
No, no!
不 我只是下不了决心      好吧 也许我能帮忙
No, I just can't make up my mind. Well, perhaps I can help.
怎么?      理论上 我不该给您看这个
How? Technically, I shouldn't be showing you this.
怎么? 我不是首相吗      毫无疑问
Why not? I'm Prime Minister, aren't I? Indeed you are!
所以我才不该给您看
That's why I shouldn't show it to you.
是国防部内部文件草案 国防大臣都没看过
It's a Ministry of Defence internal paper. The Secretary hasn't seen it yet.
但您看 其中对就业大臣的计划
But it casts grave doubts
提出了严重质疑      是吗?
on the plan. Does it?
里面指出 他提到的许多贵重建筑
Many of the valuable buildings
根本不能卖
he quotes can't be sold.
有些是古迹 有些受规划控制 搬迁成本太过高昂
Some are listed, some have planning controls. The cost would be prohibitive.
还会在伦敦周边和东英格兰造成严重失业
It'd create unemployment in the Home Counties and East Anglia
第3部分 一页页都是基于战略考量的反对意见
and in Part 3 there are objections on the grounds of military strategy.
这些都真实可靠吗?      都是国防部的手笔
And all this is honest and accurate? It comes from the Ministry of Defence.
即便如此 也有可能真实可靠吧
Even so, it COULD be honest and accurate.
告诉你 我觉得公众有权知道这些
You know, I think the public has a right to know this.
这是顶级机密文件
It is a top-secret document.
话说回来 军官们是出了名的口没遮拦
On the other hand, the service chiefs are notorious for their indiscretion.
有可能流到某个不负责任的记者手中
It could find its way into the hands of some irresponsible journalist.
对 或者某几个...      某几个 是的 首相
Quite. Or several irresponsible... Several, indeed, Prime Minister.
当然 我绝不能参与      当然不能
Of course, I could never be a party to that. Certainly not.
那么 首相 我们是不是要
So, shall we defer further discussion
把就业大臣计划的讨论
of the Employment Secretary's plan
无限制延期?
to an unspecified future date?
好 不管它了
Yeah, let's drop it.
首相 我先疏浚管道去了
Prime Minister. Meanwhile, I'll go and attend to the plumbing.
他什么时候会泄密?      我要他泄密了吗 伯纳?
When's he going to leak it? Did I ask for a leak, Bernard?
倒没有明说...不 您没有      对 我没有
Well, not in so many... No, you didn't. No, I didn't.
我偶尔开些内部新闻发布会 可我从不泄密
I occasionally have confidential press briefings, but I have never leaked.
又是不规则动词 对吧?
Another irregular verb
某甲开内部新闻发布会 某乙泄密
I give confidential press briefings, you leak,
某丙被控违反官方保密法2A条款
he's been charged under Section 2A of the Official Secrets Act.
早安 首相      早安
Good morning, Prime Minister. Morning.
早安 首相      你们看报纸了吗?
Good morning. Have you seen the papers?
看了      达德利回应了泄密的事
Indeed. Dudley's replied to the press about that leak.
他说他没泄密 有人害他的
he said he leaked nothing
他要求公开调查
He's demanded a public inquiry.
真惊人      调查从来查不出泄密人
Shocking. Inquiries never find the true source of a leak.
但我们知道是谁 您要我们...      伯纳
But we know the true source. You asked us... Bernard.
你该不是暗示
You're not suggesting
泄密是我指使的吧
I authorised this leak?
不 我...没错...就是说...我想起来了 抱歉
Er, no, I... er... That is, yes. Um, I mean... Oh, I remember now. Sorry.
你想起什么了 伯纳?      您说什么就是什么
What do you remember, Bernard? Whatever you want.
我要公众相信根本没有分歧
I want the public to know there are no divisions.
可确实有啊      我不想它们加倍
But there are. I don't want them multiplied.
首相 如果把分开的加倍 就回到原点了
If you multiply divisions, you get back to where you started.
把4分成2份 得2 再加倍 还是4
If you divide four by two, you get two. If you multiply it, you get four.
除非您的倍数和分数不同...
Unless you multiply different divisions...
4分2份...伯纳 请他们进来      是 首相
Four by two... Bernard, send them in. Yes, Prime Minister.
汉弗莱 我想把就业大臣留在内阁
I want to keep the Employment Secretary in the Cabinet,
国防大臣也是
and the Defence Secretary,
但我不能再放任不管了
but I can't let this row go on any longer.
我不能显得被就业大臣打败 风险太大了
I can't allow the Employment Secretary to be seen to defeat me.
那我建议您 提请委员会同意这三点
I suggest you ask the Committee to agree to these three points.
第一 内阁决议必须接受
First, they accept Cabinet's decision.
第二 要有个冷却期 讨论中止
Secondly, there's a cooling-off period with no further discussion.
最后 未来所有讲话和媒体声明
Further, that all speeches and press statements
要由内阁办公室审查
are cleared with the Cabinet Office.
很好 这就没问题了 对 第一点 冷却期
Splendid. That should do it, yes. Point one, a cooling-off period.
第二点 讨论中止...
Point two, no more decisions or discussions...
不对 第二是什么来着?
No, what was the second one?
我记不住...      我写给您 首相
I can't quite... I'll write it down for you, Prime Minister.
先生们 请坐
Ah, gentlemen, please be seated.
你们都拿到议程副本了
You've all had a copy of the agenda.
第一项 上次会议纪要
Item one, minutes of the last meeting.
首相 抱歉 有个程序问题
Excuse me, a point of order.
我的国防机构重组计划不在议程上
My plan for defence establishment relocation is not on the agenda.
正是 达德利      为什么?
That is correct, Dudley. Why not?
因为泄密 媒体已经在口诛笔伐
This leaking is creating a damaging press row.
我不能让内阁显得有分歧
I can't allow the Cabinet to seem divided.
是有分歧      所以尤其不能显出来
It is divided. That's why it mustn't look it.
事情很复杂 所以我决定延期讨论
It's a very complex issue and I've decided to defer further discussion.
我不明白 您上次还支持的      不 我没有
You were in favour of it last time. No, I wasn't.
您有 大家都支持 除了国防部      不 大家没有
You were! So was everyone, except Defence. No, they weren't.
他们有 您承诺深入讨论的
They were! You promised further discussion!
抱歉打扰一下  我不能苟同
Um... I'm sorry to interrupt, but I think not.
什么?      没有过这种承诺
What? There was no such promise.
首相也从未支持提案 否则 会议纪要上会有记载
And the PM did not support. If he had, it would appear in the minutes.
上面没有      没有吗?
It doesn't. Doesn't it?
首相 为什么我要求的深入讨论
Prime Minister, why was my request for a
和您的回答没有记载?
further discussion not minuted?
我...      首相
I... Er, Prime Minister.
委员会讨论或决议的共性是
It is characteristic of committee decisions that
每个与会人员都对它记忆犹新
every member has a vivid recollection of them
而每人的记忆又和别人大相径庭
and that every member's recollection differs from every other member's.
因此按惯例 所谓官方决议 是且只是
Consequently, we accept the convention that official decisions are those
官方人员记入纪要的决议
recorded in the minutes by the officials.
因此顺理成章 不可避免地
From which it emerges, with an elegant inevitability,
任何官方达成的决议
that any officially reached decision
都会被官方记入纪要
will have been recorded by the officials.
而官方纪要里没有的
Any decision not recorded
就从未被官方达成过
has not been officially reached,
哪怕个别成员自以为记得有过
even if one or more members believe they can recollect it,
因此 就这件事来说 如果官方确实达成了决议
so, in this case, if the decision had been officially reached,
它一定会在官方纪要里
it would've been recorded by the officials,
但它没记录 因此不存在
and it isn't, so it wasn't.
我说吧
Told you so.
这是篡改 首相...
This is a fiddle! Prime Minister...
别说了 这必须停止      是的 必须停下来
No, this must stop. Yes, it must!
我拟了三点计划 我们都必须遵守
I have drawn up a three-point plan to which we must all adhere.
第一...第一是什么来着?
Point one... What was point one?
谢谢 第一 每人都必须接受集体决议 达德利
Oh, thank you. Point one, everyone will accept collective decisions, Dudley.
我很乐意 哪些是集体决议?      我说了算
I am perfectly willing to. How are they defined? I define them.
第二 国防重组事宜进入冷却期
Point two, there will be a cooling-off period on defence relocations.
第三...看不清 申什么?      不 审查所有讲话...
Point three... Can't read this. Cleaning what? No, CLEARING all speeches...
哦 对 所有讲话和媒体声明
All speeches and press statements
要由内阁办公室清查
must be cleared with the Cabinet Office.
我不能接受第二点 根本没讨论过
We can't cool off discussion on
冷却讨论从何谈起?
something that hasn't been discussed yet
我也绝不接受我的言论都得由他审查
and I cannot accept that anything I say must be cleared by HIM.
他不能查禁我想说的话
He won't clear what I want to say.
这是我的决定 你必须接受      我不接受
That is my decision and you must accept it. I won't accept it!
达德利 恐怕你得考虑自己的位置了
Well, Dudley, I'm afraid you must consider your position.
首相      什么?
Prime Minister. Yes?
我有些消息 您要先听坏消息吗?
I have news. Do you want the bad news first?
还有坏的和好的啊      不 坏的和更坏的
There's bad news and good news? No, bad news and worse news.
就业大臣辞职了 这是辞呈
The Employment Secretary has resigned. His letter.
我真不想失去他的      您要听更坏的吗?
I didn't want to lose him. Would you like the worse news now?
他指控您专制独裁 大兴总统制政府
He's accused you of being dictatorial.
好吧 这我倒不介意
Oh. Well, I don't mind that.
其实也不错吧? 人民喜欢铁腕领导人
Rather good, isn't it? People like to know they've got a strong leader.
独裁是吗?      对 铁腕领导人会很新奇的
Dictatorial, eh? It will be a new pleasure for them.
不 不会的      不 不会的
No, it won't. No, it won't.
汉弗莱 我真为他的辞职难过
Humphrey, I'm upset about this resignation.
是你的三点计划激发的
YOUR three-point plan provoked it.
没错 首相 可据我了解
Yes, indeed, Prime Minister, but I understand
就业大臣无论如何都打算辞职了
the Employment Secretary was planning to resign soon in any case.
是吗? 为什么 什么时候?
Was he? Why? And when?
财政预算发表日 理由是
On budget day, as it was expected to give him
拨给他的失业应对资金不够
insufficient money to deal with unemployment.
天 那就丢人了      但会让他名声大噪的
Damaging. It would've made him extremely popular.
也许还是我赶走他好
Perhaps it's as well I made him go.
首相 您处理得简直绝妙
Prime Minister, you handled it brilliantly!
您逼他为一件晦涩的
You forced him to resign on an obscure
行政问题辞职 您占主动
administrative issue of your choosing,
而不是他自行选定的政策问题
rather than on a policy issue of his choosing.
没人会支持他 因为没人明白怎么回事 神来之笔
Nobody will support him because nobody will understand why he's gone
对 是挺绝的 对吧?
Yes... it was pretty clever, wasn't it?
无懈可击 首相
Oh, masterly!
这份媒体声明 您可以考虑发布
Here's a press statement you might release.
要我打给比尔吗?      不 伯纳 我来找比尔
Shall I phone Bill? No, Bernard, I shall phone Bill.
专制独裁 是吗?
Dictatorial, hm?
我倒不知道他打算为预算案辞职呢
I didn't know he was thinking of resigning over the budget.
我也不知道      您说这不是真的?
Nor did I. You mean it's not true?
我没说是真的 我说据我理解是真的
I didn't say it was true. I said I understood it to be true.
也许我误会了      您也不知是真是假?
I may have misunderstood. So you don't know it's true?
我不能说是假的 可能是真的
I don't know it's not. It might be.
一切都可能是真的
Anything might be!
正是 有进步 伯纳
Exactly. Well done, Bernard.
记下来 比尔
Take this down, Bill.
"我心存疑虑 我们审查了他的计划"
"I'm puzzled because his plan was being studied,
"发现成本可能远高于预期"
but there was a danger of much greater cost
"却不能必然达成促进就业的目标"
"without necessarily achieving the employment objectives."
好 印好了送来给我
Fine. Send it up to me when it's typed.
汉弗莱 看来这次又多亏你了
Well, Humphrey, looks as if you've done me a good turn.
的确 首相      不过真可惜
Yes, indeed, Prime Minister. Pity, though.
是啊 可他确实阴谋反对您 您自己说的
Yes. But he was plotting against you, you said so yourself.
对 等等 我有主意了
Yes. Hold on, I've got an idea!
首相
Prime Minister!
既然就业大臣走了 我们可以重启计划了
Now that the Employment Secretary's gone, we could reinstate the plan!
可是...
But...
明白了吧 我现在可以放手去干
I could press on with it now and
不会显得软弱 而会显得强悍
it won't look like weakness, but strength!
可整个目的就是...      是什么?
But the whole point was... Was what?
该不是为了阻止计划吧?      不不
It wasn't to stop the plan, surely? No, no, no, no, no.
是为了...呃...
It was to... um... um... er... er...
树立您的威信      正是 我已经完成了
...establish your authority. Exactly. And I've done that.
所以 如果重启提案 就能表明我并没反对
So, if we recreate the plan, it'll show I wasn't against it
达德利的辞职就没意义了 对吧?
and that Dudley's resignation was pointless, right?
就列为下次会议第一项议程 好吗?
Put it top of the agenda for the next Cabinet... OK?
是 首相
Yes, Prime Minister.
(注: 本集暗讽1985-85年
英国Westland直升机事件)
破烂熊字幕组-==www.RagBear.com==-